<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A step to the Bath with a character of the place.</title>
            <author>Ward, Edward, 1667-1731.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67525</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W759</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218893</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830446</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830446</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34897</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67525)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34897)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2023:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A step to the Bath with a character of the place.</title>
                  <author>Ward, Edward, 1667-1731.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed and sold by J. How, in the Ram-Head Inn-Yard, in Fanchurch-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Edward Ward.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement on verso of title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bath (England) --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bath (England) --  Fiction --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34897:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A STEP TO THE BATH: WITH A CHARACTER OF THE PLACE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Second Edition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed and Sold by <hi>J. How,</hi> in the <hi>Ram-Head Inn-Yard,</hi> in <hi>Fanchurch-ſtreet,</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:34897:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books Printed and Sold by</hi> J. How, <hi>in the</hi> Ram-Head-Inn-Yard <hi>in</hi> Fenchurch-Street; <hi>and by</hi> M. Fabian, <hi>at</hi> Mercers-Chappel.</head>
            <p n="1">1. SOt's Paradiſe: Or the Humours of a Derby-Ale-Houſe: With a Satyr upon the Ale. Price Six Pence.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A Trip to <hi>Jamaica:</hi> With a True Character of the People and Iſland Price Six Pence.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Eccleſia &amp; Factio.</hi> A Dialogue between <hi>Bow-Steeple-Dragon,</hi> and the <hi>Exchange-Graſhoper.</hi> Price Six pence.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Poet's Ramble after Riches. With Reflections upon a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Corporation. Alſo the Author's Lamentation in the time of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity. Price Six pence.</p>
            <p n="5">5. A Trip to <hi>New-England.</hi> With a Character of the Country and People, both <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Indians.</hi> Price Six pence.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Modern Religion, &amp; Ancient Loyalty: A Dialogue. Price Six Pence.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The World Bewitch'd. A Dialogue between two Aſtrologers and the Author. With Infallible Predictions of what will happen from the <hi>Vices</hi> and <hi>Villanies</hi> Practis'd in <hi>Court, City,</hi> and <hi>Country.</hi> Price Six pence.</p>
            <p n="8">8. A Walk to <hi>Iſlington:</hi> With a Deſcription of New <hi>Tunbridge</hi>-Wells, and <hi>Sadler's</hi> Muſick-Houſe. Price Six pence.</p>
            <p n="9">9. The Humours of a Coffee-Houſe: A Comedy. Price Six Pence.</p>
            <p n="10">10. A Frolick to <hi>Horn-Fair.</hi> With a Walk from Cuckold's-Point thro' <hi>Deptford</hi> and <hi>Greenwich.</hi> Price Six pence.</p>
            <p n="11">11. The Dancing-School. With the Adventures of the <hi>Eaſter</hi>-Holy-Days. Price Six pence.</p>
            <p n="12">12. The Firſt Volume of the LONDON-SPY: In Twelve Parts.</p>
            <p n="13">13. The Second Volume of the LONDON-SPY: In Six Parts. Price Six Pence each; or they may be had both Volumes Bound to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; and alſo Bound with the reſt of the Authors Writings.</p>
            <p n="14">14. The Metamorphos'd Beau, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Price Six pence.</p>
            <p n="15">15. The Engliſh Nun: Or, a Comical Deſcription of a Nunnery. With the Lives and Intrigues of the Prieſts and Nuns Price Six Pence.</p>
            <p n="16">16. Laugh and be Fat: Or, an Antidote againſt Melancholy. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining great variety of Comical Intrigues in Town and Country. To which is added <hi>Nine Delightful Tales.</hi> Price One Shilling.</p>
            <p n="17">17. A Step to the Bath: With a Character of the Place. Price Six Pence.</p>
            <p n="18">18. Labour in Vain: Or, what Signifies Little or Nothing, <hi>viz.</hi> I. The Poor Mans Petition at Court. II. Expectation of Benefit from a Covetous Man in his Life time. III The Marriage of an Old Man to a Young Woman. IV. Endeavours to Regulate Mens Manners by Preaching or Writing. V. Being a <hi>Jacobite.</hi> VI. Confining an Inſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Debtor. VII. Promiſe of Secrecy in a Conſpiracy. VIII. An Enquiry after a Place.</p>
            <p n="19">19. The Reformer. Expoſing the Vices of the Age: In ſeveral Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters. <hi>viz.</hi> 1. The Vitious Courtier. 2. The Debauch'd Parſon. 3. The Factious Hypocrite. 4. The Preciſe Quaker. 5. The Covetous Miſer. 6. The Prodigal Son. 7. The City Letcher. 8. The Inſatiate Wife. 9. The Amorous Maid. 10. The Beau Apprentice. 11. The City Mob. 12. The Country Squire.</p>
            <p n="20">20. The Rambling Rakes: Or, London Libertines. Price Six Pence.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:34897:2"/>
            <head>A STEP TO THE BATH.</head>
            <p>THE Town, and its Diverſions, being grown as Stale as a Caſt-off Miſtreſs; and the chiefeſt of its Inhabitants withdrawn to their Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Pleaſures; and Duns as Impudent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>D</hi>— the <hi>Poulterian Officer:</hi> So that being bereav'd of the one, &amp; damnably Fatigu'd by the other; Neceſſity, the Mother of Invention, oblig'd me to take a Country Journey, for Self-Preſervation ſake; having Money to <hi>Spend,</hi> tho' none to <hi>Pay.</hi> And the laſt Summers Expedition at the <hi>Wells,</hi> not agreeing with my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Conſtitution, and my Inclinations being bent after Novelties, I reſolv'd to Steer my Courſe <hi>Weſtward,</hi> to ſee what Pleaſure thoſe <hi>Pools of Iniquity,</hi> call'd the <hi>BATH,</hi> would afford me. In order for which, I preſently took Hack, and bid him drive me to that terrible Sign, the <hi>Sarazens-Head</hi> in <hi>Fryday-Street,</hi> where I gave Earneſt for a Place in the following <hi>Mondays</hi> Coach; but being <hi>Saturday,</hi> and late in the Seaſon, I thought I ſhould have no reaſon to Curſe my Company, for mine was the firſt that was taken: But my Tun-Belly'd Hoſteſs, to Encourage me, ſaid, <hi>That not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding 'twas ſo late in the Week, ſhe doubted not but there would be more Places taken before Night.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In hopes of which, I left her, to prepare for my approaching Journey; and Money being the Life of the Cauſe, I muſter'd up a pretty tolerable Sum, and for conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of Carriage, converted it into the Nobleſt of Metals. Then I began to think of the Redemption of ſeveral Captivated Neceſſaries, which an Unlucky Accident had brought into Bondage; as an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltramarine Joſeph,</hi> a Pocket Monitor of <hi>Tompion</hi>'s Compoſing, and a Silver Hilted <hi>Ripp</hi> of the <hi>Iſebrook</hi>'s Temper; three as neceſſary Implements for a <hi>Traveller,</hi> as <hi>Gooſe, Yard,</hi> and <hi>Sheers,</hi> for a <hi>Taylor.</hi> Well, to <hi>Egypt</hi> I went, and Redeem'd them from Slavery.</p>
            <p>And by reaſon I would be ready on <hi>Monday</hi> Morning, I went to Lye at the Inn on <hi>Sunday</hi> Night; and Enquiring of the Tapſter what Company I was like to have, he ſaid more he believ'd than I deſir'd; for there was four Places taken juſt after I went, and three of the Paſſengers were in the Houſe, and to lie there that Night; the other was for a Merchant of <hi>Briſtol.</hi> Then asking what thoſe in the Houſe were, he told me two Gentlewomen and their Maid Servant, who were juſt going to Supper. Whereupon I bid him go and give my Service to 'em, and tell 'em I was to Travel with 'em to Morrow, and ſhould take it as a great Favour, if they would pleaſe to Honour me ſo far, as to Admit me into their Company, for I was alone. The Fellow brought Word they deſir'd me to Walk in, and they ſhould be very glad of mine.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34897:3"/>This being what I wanted, in I went; and after a few Ceremonial Complements, and Begging Pardon for my Rudeneſs, I told them I was afraid I ſhould have gone alone, but now I found I ſhould be Bleſs'd beyond my Hopes, in having the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, or rather Happineſs, of their good Company. <hi>I Wiſh, Sir,</hi> reply'd one of them, <hi>It may anſwer your Expectation, for our Sex is counted but very indifferent Company to Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel with, and you are like to be Fatigu'd with three of us.</hi> As for Children, and Teſty Age, Madam, anſwer'd I, I agree in the Opinion; but otherwiſe, condemn it as Erroneous: And for your Number, The More the Merrier. <hi>That's according as it proves, Sir,</hi> ſaid ſhe; <hi>neither would I have you Flatter your ſelf too ſoon, leaſt your hopes ſhould prove abortive, but rather referr you to old</hi> Saffold<hi>'s Advice,</hi> Read, Try, Judge, and ſpeak as you find. I muſt confeſs, Madam, anſwer'd I, Experience is the only Touch-ſtone; but I ſhall be mightily deceiv'd in my Politicks, if it does not make good my Aſſertion. <hi>I Preſume, Sir,</hi> ſaid the other Lady, <hi>You have Studyed</hi> Saunders, <hi>and are well Vers'd in</hi> Phyſiognomy, <hi>or you could never pretend to ſo much Fore-knowledge.</hi> At which I Crav'd the Honour of ſeeing her Hand, telling her, I had ſome little Skill in <hi>Palmeſtry,</hi> by which Art I perceiv'd ſhe requir'd not much Caſtration; which made them both Laugh: And the firſt Lady ask'd me, if I had any Skill in <hi>Chiromancy,</hi> for the ſame Author Profeſt both. I told her no; but was ſatisfied ſhe had; for her Charms had rais d ſuch a Spirit in me, that I knew not how to lay it without her Aſſiſtance. <hi>I never underſtood</hi> Magick, <hi>I Proteſt, Sir,</hi> reply'd ſhe, <hi>and am mightily afraid of a Spirit: Therefore let's Diſcourſe no more of ſuch <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nruly things, that neither of to know how to Govern.</hi> Your Power is as abſolute in Laying as in Raiſing of them, Lady, anſwer'd I; but ſince 'tis your Pleaſure, your Command ſhall be Obey'd, and I'll ſhape my Diſcourſe to what Subject you Pleaſe.</p>
            <p>But Supper coming in, they deſir'd me to ſit down with them, and having more Manners than to refuſe ſo good a Proffer, I comply'd with their Requeſt, and fed very Heartily. The Glaſs went Briskly about, that we were as Merry, as a Knot of Jovial Tinkers over a Cup of Nappy-Ale, and I began to like my Company extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary well<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but the Charming Inchantreſs and I, interchang'd ſo many learing Ogles, that I could hardly mind our Diſcourſe; yet I underſtood ſo much, that ſhe was a <hi>Widow,</hi> the other a <hi>Wife,</hi> and both Siſters, and alſo Strangers to the Place they were going to, as well as I; and had no other Call but Recreation; But I was for fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Scriptures, in Comforting the <hi>Widow.</hi> Supper being ended, they call'd for a Bill, which was preſently brought; out I lugg'd, and was going to Diſcharge, but they begg'd my Pardon, and would by no means ſuffer me; telling me I muſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the Rule that is generally obſerv'd in Travelling, for the <hi>Major</hi> of either Sex to Treat the <hi>Minor.</hi> I muſt Acknowledge, Ladies, ſaid I, 'tis an Old Cuſtome ſo to do, but we are not now on the Road; however that Avail'd not, they pleaded the Prerogative of the Majority, and carry'd it <hi>Nolens Volens.</hi> Seeing they were ſo Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute. I diſpenc'd with the Affront, conſidering I had often put up a greater, and would not preſs too hard, leaſt it ſhould prevail; but that was a needleſs Thought, for the Young Widow drew from between her Snowy Breaſts, a Purſe Cramm'd as full of <hi>Yellow-Boys,</hi> as a Clerk of a Markets Bag of <hi>Copper John</hi>'s, and Diſcharg'd the whole. Seeing of which, I thought I could do no leſs in Honour than call for my Flask; Craving Leave to preſent them with it as my Foy; and being a little Elevated with the Noble Juice, we were as Jocund and Frolickſome, as a Countrey-Vicar at a Goſſiping. In came the Wine, without diſputing who ſhould pay for it. But at laſt, Night, the Lovers Bliſs, and Bane of good Company, Oblig'd us to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw to our Chambers. Upon which, I told the Ladies, I ſhould think the time ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry tedious till I ſhould be ſo happy as to Enjoy their good Company again. <hi>We are apter to believe Sir,</hi> anſwer'd they, <hi>You will think the Journey ſo, by reaſon of the Dull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it.</hi> Say what I will, Ladies, ſaid I, you Foy'l me with my own Weapons, and are pleas'd to Retort my Words to their own Centre. So after a profound Cringe or two, with a Gripe of the Paw, and as many Amorous Glances at my Charming Widow, who return'd me the like, we parted: But never any happy Bridegroom Long'd for the Approaching Night, more than I for the ſucceeding Morning.</p>
            <p>No ſooner had I enter'd my Chamber, but I found a Secret Paſſion had poſſeſt my Soul, and I was all on Fire: Ye Powers, cry'd I, what ſtrange Fever's this that Rages
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34897:3"/>in my Breaſt, and Riots in my Blood? Not Liquid Fire, by its firſt Cauſe Fomented, burns Fiercer in Earths Center, than I flame within. Tame this Unruly Flame, or touch her Heart that firſt Kindl'd it, with a Cole from the ſame Altar. Nay 'tis impoſſible to relate how violent my Paſſion rag'd; but in Love I was, that's certain; but whether her Purſe or Perſon begat this Flame, is a very Nice Queſtion, and I proteſt I know not; for, as Mr. <hi>Cowley</hi> ſays,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Gold alone does Paſſion move;</l>
               <l>Gold Monopolizes Love.</l>
            </q>
            <p>For Gold has Unreſiſtable Charms as well as Beauty; is of a Corroding Quality; of an Attractive Nature, and bears a great influence o'er the Opticks. And 'twas very probable that Purſe was only Prologue to a far greater Sum; ſo by conſequence muſt needs have ſome Operation; not but the Ladies were both very Amiable, in the Bloom of Vigorous Youth, bore a good Aſpect, had no mean Air, Free, and without Reſerve in their Converſation; and their Deportment declar'd them of no Vulgar Quality. But the Charming Golden Widow was the Idol of my Soul, Subject of my Thoughts, and Center of my Wiſhes; Muſing on whom, at laſt dull <hi>Morpheus</hi> Seal'd my Eyes, to relieve my Captivated Senſes.</p>
            <q>
               <l>But, Oh ye Gods! No Reſt could I obtain,</l>
               <l>The Charming Fair, did o'er my Slumbers Reign;</l>
               <l>And in ſtrange Dreams Augment my Rapid Flame.</l>
            </q>
            <p>By that time Forked <hi>Cynthia</hi> had withdrawn her influence, and bright <hi>Aurora</hi> roſe from <hi>Thetis</hi> Lap, I ſhook off the Drowſy God, and bleſt the joyful Day. Looking out of my Window, I perceiv'd they were preparing for our Journey, which made me Rig with all imaginable ſpeed; and as I was going down, who ſhould I meet but my Cherubimical Widdow, equip'd like a Goddeſs, and Adorn'd with Ribbon like the Fore-Horſe of a Country-Team? After we had given each other the Time of the Day, <hi>Lord Sir,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>Are you but juſt up? Why we are almoſt Ready to go; certainly you Slept very Sound.</hi> No Madam anſwer'd I, ſince I have had the Happineſs of ſeeing you, Reſt has been a ſtranger to my Breſt. <hi>Have I diſturbed you Sir,</hi> ſaid ſhe? <hi>If ſo, I ask your Pardon, and am ſorry for it.</hi> Ye Gods, cry'd I, what ſhall I ſay? Or how ſhall I expreſs my ſelf? Inſpire my Tongue with Eloquence, thou God of Love, to make her ſenſible of my Pain. Oh Madam, cry'd I, you are Innocent of your Crime, and Guilty of the Fact: You have Robb'd me of my Reſt, Fir'd my Blood, and Stolen my Heart; ſee how it Hovers o'er your Panting Breaſt, and fain would gain Admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. <hi>I Vow Sir,</hi> anſwer'd ſhe, <hi>Your Diſcourſe is ſo Myſterious, that it wants another</hi> Oedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus <hi>to unfold. And for what you are Pleas'd to charge me withal, is a falſe Accuſation; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have I Vacancy to Entertain it.</hi> Ah Madam, reply'd I, I could ſoon convince you of your Error, if you would give me leave to ſearch in a certain Corner you have about you, that ſhall be Nameleſs. At which ſhe Bluſh'd, and told me I was mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Miſtaken: But allow it ſo, ſince 'twas Ignorantly committed, and without any premeditated deſign, ſhe hop'd I would be ſo generous as to Forgive her. Never Madam, ſaid I, unleſs you vouchſafe to caſt an Eye of Pity, and Commiſerate the Condition of your Languiſhing Lover, on whom the God of Love, if there be any ſuch a Diety, hath Empty'd his whole Artillery, and pierc'd my Heart with your all-Conquering Eyes: <hi>O Fye, Sir,</hi> anſwer'd ſhe, <hi>this is meer Railery, and only for your Diverſion, a thing Cuſtomary with you General Lovers, in whom every New Face Creates a new Flame; of the Libertines Opinion, that a Woman, after ſhe is once Enjoy'd, grows Dull and Inſipid; and what you have now ſo ſolemnly pretended to me, is no more then you have already done to half our Sex, if poſſible; and ſuch I take it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By my Soul I thought ſhe was a Witch by her gueſſing ſo right, and was a going to tell her ſo, for every Syllable ſhe utter'd was as true as an Oracle. But finding by her Parlying I had made a Breach, I reſolv'd to Storm the Caſtle. If you Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour any ſuch thought of me, Madam, anſwer'd I, by Heaven you do me wrong; for ſo pure is my Flame, and ſo Aſſiduous my Paſſion, without you give me ſpeedy
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:34897:4"/>hopes, I ſhall fall a Sacrifice to your diſdain, and <hi>Phoenix</hi>-like, expire in my own Flames. <hi>'Tis but Breathing a Vein Sir,</hi> anſwer'd ſhe, <hi>and your Feavour will ſoon abate.</hi> Oh Madam, cry'd I, how can you be ſo Cruel? You gave the Wound, but Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter a contrary Cure. Wrack me no longer thus with Doubts and Fears, either retaliate me in the ſame Nature, or pronounce my Doom; for on your Lips my Fate depends. <hi>Indeed Sir,</hi> anſwer'd ſhe, <hi>that requires more Conſideration than the time will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of now: Yet take this for your Satisfaction, if your Character and Quality anſwers your Appearance, and your Paſſion be real, you need not diſpond of the Entertainment of that Triſle you are pleaſed to Charge me withal, but it ſhall find a Reception Suitable to its Merits.</hi> At which ſhe Sigh'd, and ſaid our Company waited for us, but in the Evening would take an Opportunity to diſcourſe further of it. Now Madam, you have ruiſed my drooping Spirits to an Extaſie of Joy, anſwer'd I; Pardon my Preſumption, and Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt proceeding, I beſeech you, in taking this opportunity to reveal my Paſſion, and impute it to nothing but Love, Almighty Love, for what will not a ſinking Wretch catch hold on, to ſave his Miſerable Life?</p>
            <p>At which we ſeparated, and joyn'd our Company, who were preparing for an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidote againſt Faſting, which we had ſcarcely compleated, but were call'd on to Board our Leathern-Conveniency, and were Pen'd up like the Beaſts in the Ark; but I took care to have my Miſtreſs my Oppoſite, and being ſettled, <hi>Whip</hi> proceeded on his Journey, and having a plentiful Mornings Draught<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Tickled his Cittel, drove like <hi>Jehu,</hi> and ſoon convey'd us to the Sign of <hi>Englands Champion</hi> at <hi>Cole-brook,</hi> an Inn famous for an Hoſteſs, and Extravagant Bills for ſhort Commons.</p>
            <p>Having refreſh'd our ſelves with a good Breakfaſt, we re-enter'd our Coop, and was but very indifferent Company, for our <hi>Maſculine</hi> Traveller, the Married Lady, and Mrs. <hi>Betty</hi> the Chamber-Maid, had a Long Game at Noddy: However it preſented me with ſeveral Opportunities of Saluting my Widow, and Exerciſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of Falm Letchery; but being come to <hi>Reading,</hi> we Din'd at the <hi>Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal-Nabb,</hi> where our Landlord was as Remarkable for his Bulk, as our late Hoſteſs for her Tail; formerly he was a profeſt Baptiſt, but being choſen one of the Head Loobies of the Corporation, he renounc'd his Religion, Embrac'd the Faith, and was Chriſtned <hi>Lumpus;</hi> his Corps is of the ſize of a <hi>Rhinoceros,</hi> Meaſures full three Yards in the Waſte, and his Legs bigger about than the Piers of the Town Bridge; the Doctor of the Pariſh hath excommunicated him from the Church; becauſe his Snor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring not only drowns his Voice, but diſturbs the whole Congregation. Being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd of the Church, he then took the Fleſh, and is reported to have overlaid three of his Servants. Having now ſtock'd our ſelves with ſubſtantial Belly-Timber, and Liquor'd our Whiſtles, we purſu'd our Journey, and were more Sociable; the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies oblig'd as with ſeveral Songs, which they perform'd with an Excellent Voice, and good Judgment: But my Thoughts were chiefly Ruminating on the Fair Object before me, and how to manage my Amour at Night, every freſh Glance diſcovered conceal'd Beauties, nor was ſhe unſenſible of my Anguiſh, for her repeated Sighs betray'd her yielding Heart.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Oh what Caeleſtial Motion had her Eyes!</l>
               <l>Her Panting Breaſts, how they did fall and riſe!</l>
               <l>Conſpiring both to fall my Sacrifice.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And our Merchant took Notice of her Sighs, and ask'd her the Reaſon; ſhe told him 'twas only a Fooliſh Cuſtom; but I believe had he ask'd me, I could have given him a better Account. But come, Fellow-Travellers, ſaid he, will you pleaſe to take a Dram of Right <hi>Nants?</hi> A good Cordial on the Road, and will digeſt our Dinner; I proteſt I forgot it in the Morning: So we accepted of his kindneſs, and drain'd his Bottle: But Promiſed to recruit it the firſt opportunity; and to paſs the time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, we Engag'd Mrs <hi>Pert</hi> to Sing a Song, and our Merchant and I promis'd to tell a Story: She Pleaded ſhe could not Sing, but would oblige us in relating a very ſtrange Accident lately diſcover'd; which was as followeth.</p>
            <p>About fifteen year ſince, There was a noted Tradeſman near <hi>Aldgate,</hi> had two Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, a Son and Daughter, the Son was Aged about fifteen Years, and the Daughter
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:34897:4"/>twelve; he had a deſire to put his Son Prentice to ſome good Trade in the City, and gave him his choice, but he was very much A verſe to it, his Inclinations being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together for the Sea, and nothing would ſerve him but a <hi>Tarpaulin</hi> Maſter. At laſt his Father with much Regret Conſented to it, and put him to a Maſter of a Ship that was bound for a Trading Voyage up the <hi>Streights:</hi> At which the Young Man was Extraordinary Glad, took Leave of his Friends, and went Aboard with great Joy; but before three Months was Expir'd, News arriv'd that they were taken by the <hi>Algerines,</hi> from whom at that time there was no Redemption: The News of which, and a Conſiderable Loſs the Old Man had lately Suſtain'd by Fire, not only Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd his Condition to a mean Subſiſtance, but broke his Heart, nor did his Wife long Survive him; and with the remains of their decay'd Fortune, the Poor <hi>Orphan</hi> was put to a Sempſtreſs; but before her Time was Expir'd, one of <hi>Exeter</hi> fell in Love with her, Marry'd her, and took her with him to <hi>Exon,</hi> unknown to her Friends or Acquaintance; in a few Years after he left her a Widow, no Children, and but little to Truſt to; which to improve, ſhe ſet up her Trade, and maintain'd her ſelf very Handſomely, Living in good Credit. But her Unhappy Brother, who had the Misfortune to be a Slave, was bought by one that Liv'd ſever. Leagues up in the Country, never having any Opportunity of ſending to <hi>England,</hi> his Friends diſpair'd of ever ſeeing him again, and gave him over for Loſt. But ſee how Providence Order'd it, his Maſter Dyed, and by reaſon he had been a good Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, not only Bequeath'd him his Liberty, but alſo a great Sum of Money to Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain him; and his Miſtreſs, who had often given him ſeveral Evident Teſtimonies of her Affections, wou'd have Marry'd him, provided he would Renounce his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and Embrace the <hi>Mabometan,</hi> which he deny'd to do; but her Love was ſo Violent, or rather Luſt ſo Raging, that it over-flow'd the Bounds of Modeſty, and by the Allurements of her Gold, intic'd him to ſatisfie her Exorbitant Deſires, by which means he had gottten a very Conſiderable Eſtate. But the Natural Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation for his own Native Country, and great Deſire to ſee his Friends, out-Ballanc'd the Embraces of his Miſtreſs, whoſe Gold was more prevailing than her Charms, and came the firſt Opportunity for <hi>England,</hi> and in a ſhort time Arriv'd at <hi>Plymouth,</hi> the next day reach'd <hi>Exon;</hi> and having preſent occaſion for ſome Linnen, he Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentally goes into his Unknown Siſters Shop and furniſh'd himſelf, then Poſts for <hi>London;</hi> where to his great Grief, he found, as I have already Related; and by no meant could get any Information of his Siſter, his long Abſence not only bereav'd him of his Friends, but alſo of all his former Acquaintance; that he was become an <hi>Alien</hi> in the Place of his Nativity. The Deprivation of which, was an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Trouble to him, and the only way to Redreſs it, he thought would be to Alter his Condition; he Coveted not Riches, but Content, to Compenſate for his hard Fate. But, Oh, how often are we Deceiv'd in our Expectations, and our hopes Fruſtrated by an All-Seeing Power? His Fancy preſented none ſo Charming to his Eyes as the <hi>Exeter</hi> Widow: Nay, ſo great was his Paſſion, that immediately he goes down, Courts her, and in a ſhort time Married her, brings her up to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> takes a Houſe, and Liv'd very Happily together, had two Children by her; and no Diſcourſe as yet of their Parents happened between them. But ſee how Fate Ordain'd it! Not long ſince, as he was Walking by <hi>Fleet-Ditch,</hi> he eſpies his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Picture Expos'd to Sale among Old Goods; which preſently he Bought, and made a very ſtrict Enquiry where they had it, thinking thereby to trace his Siſter, but 'twas ſo long ſince they bought it, that they could give him no Account; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, he imputed it to be a very Lucky Accident, had it brought home with him, and with abundance of Joy ſhows it his Wife. Telling her, 'twas the Picture of his Father, and how Accidentally he came by it: At which, ſhe was mightily ſurpris'd, and told him, <hi>If that was the Picture of his Father, (which Heaven forbid) ſhe was his own Natural Siſter:</hi> He Aſtoniſh'd at this dreadful News, ask'd her a few more queſtions, ſhe Reſolving of which, Confirm'd the Diſcovery, and hath Involv'd them into a great deal of Trouble and Conſternation of Mind; for the Eaſement of which, they have had the Opinion of ſeveral Learned Divines; who adviſe them to joyn no more in their Inceſtuous Bed, but Live after the Natural Bonds of Affinity, and ſince 'twas Ignorantly Committed, it mitigated the Crime, and they were more to be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:34897:5"/>Pittyed; and none could be ſo Barbarous, as to reflect on their Unhappy Off-Spring. But 'tis to be Fear'd, it will prove Fatal to them both, for they Labour under an Agony of Mind, that nothing but Death or Diſtraction is Expected.</p>
            <p>Her Story being Ended, the Ladies Confirm'd it, and declar'd they knew the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and it had not been Diſcover'd above two or three Years; but while we were Commiſerating their hard Fate, we came to a Vilage call'd <hi>Theal,</hi> and ſtopt at Old <hi>Mother Cleanly</hi>'s, at the Sign of the <hi>Divine Clamour;</hi> as Noted a Houſe for Bottle-Ale and Plumb-Cakes, as the <hi>Folly</hi> on the River of <hi>Thames,</hi> for bad Wine, and Lewd Whores: Nay, <hi>Slaſh</hi> declar'd he dares no more paſs by without calling, than the Forked Animals miſs <hi>Cuchold's-Point,</hi> in their Journey to <hi>Horn-Fair:</hi> But having participated, and given our Approbation on her Commodity, we Travel'd on, and our <hi>Briſtol</hi> Merchant told us, he preſum'd we were a going to the <hi>BATH</hi> for Diverſion; but his Journey to <hi>London</hi> was ſuch a Novelty, that 'twas ſcarce to be Parallel'd, and notwithſtanding it had occaſion'd him a great deal of Trouble, it might Divert us; with that we deſir'd him to Relate it, which he preſently did, after this manner:</p>
            <p>The Place of my Habitation you already know, of which I have been a Merchant almoſt this thirty year, am a Widower and have ſeveral Children, but my Eldeſt Son being very Deſirous to Live at <hi>London,</hi> I put him to an Eminent Draper in <hi>C</hi>—, but before he had Serv'd half his Time, he kept ſuch high Company, and was Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with ſo many Rakes of the Town, that his Maſter was as weary of him, as he of his Maſter; ſo I was oblig'd to take him Home, and Deſign'd to bring him up a Merchant, but the Infection he receiv'd at <hi>London,</hi> made too great an Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to be Diſcharg'd by my Documents, which often occaſion'd no ſmall differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence between us; about a Month ſince, having ſome very Urgent Buſineſs in <hi>Wales,</hi> which requir'd my Abſence for at leaſt twelve or fourteen Days, I left my Daughter to manage my Domeſtick, and he my other Affairs, and took my Journey; but that Night I left him, he ſends Word to all my Correſpondents at <hi>London,</hi> that I was Dead, (as I underſtand ſince) and that he ſhould be with them in a ſhort time, for his Father having left him a Plentiful Eſtate, he deſign'd to leave off Merchandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing. This News Startl'd my Acquaintance, and they ſent him ſeveral Letters of Condolence; and my Death paſt as Currant on the <hi>Exchange,</hi> as if it had been ſworn by twenty <hi>Iriſh</hi> Witneſſes. My Daughter who kept my Caſh, ſent him a Letter of Advice, of the Payment of ſome Bills, I had lately drawn on him, which he receiv'd and anſwer'd; he alſo Intercepted the Letters I ſent his Siſter, and about ſix days before I came Home, takes fifty Pound of my Houſe Caſh and Poſts for <hi>London,</hi> and before he Appear'd Publick, Cloths himſelf in deep Mourning, Viſits my Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondents, tells them he came to Adminiſter to his Fathers Will, and Ballance Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, and takes up of my Goldſmith 1300 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> who pay'd it him all in Gold, as he requeſted; having Accompliſh'd his Ends, Caſt off his Mourning, New Rigg'd, and now I hear he is gone for <hi>Rome,</hi> to aſſiſt at the <hi>Jubilee;</hi> but when I came home, miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of him and my Money, I preſently Conjectur'd he was gone for <hi>London,</hi> and was afraid he would take up more, therefore made all the ſpeed I could after him, to prevent it, but he was too Nimble for me; my Acquaintance was all poſſeſt with a Pannick Fear, and ſo ſurpriz'd, that they took me for a Spirit, and wou'd harldly believe their own Eyes; but I ſoon Convinc'd them of their Miſtake, and they me of my Sons Proceedings.</p>
            <p>And this is Generally the Product of ſending our Children to <hi>London:</hi> Well, had I forty, I'd never ſend any of them to <hi>London</hi> again: Now he is gone Loaded with Gold to <hi>Rome;</hi> Perhaps, about a Year or two hence, I ſhall have him return, as <hi>Light</hi> as a <hi>Common-Strumpet,</hi> as <hi>Shabby</hi> as a <hi>Broken Officer,</hi> and as <hi>Foppiſh</hi> as a <hi>City Beau;</hi> but I will never Look on him again. Make no Raſh Vow, however, Sir, ſaid I, leaſt you Repent it; (for Nature will prevail) he may Return a very Accompliſh'd Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, for Travelling conduces much to Education. <hi>Yes,</hi> anſwer'd he, <hi>As going to the Dancing-School, does Young Wenches, who if they have but a little Money are preſently Catch'd up by ſome Hopping Coxcomb or another, that hath nothing to Truſt to, but a Pair of Rotting Shanks, which are ſcarce able to ſupport his Wavering Carcaſe. I find Sir,</hi> reply'd one of the Ladies, <hi>You have a great Averſion to</hi> London <hi>Education, and the very
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:34897:5"/>Thoughts of it gives you the Spleen? Pray what is the</hi> BATH <hi>for a Nurſery? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Seaſon, that is a Place of great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Why,</hi> anſwer'd he, <hi>That's cut of the</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>into the</hi> Fire; <hi>and as Eminent for</hi> Wickedneſs <hi>as</hi> London, <hi>Bating it's</hi> Magnitude. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that, I told him, I perceiv'd be Hard ur'd no better Opinion of the Tuition of his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, than of our</hi> Metropolitan Seminary; <hi>and my Story would but Augment his Diſguſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now being got to the end of our Stage for that Day we reſerv'd mine for the next, and <hi>Newbury</hi> was as welcome to us, as <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Term to the Bauling <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</hi> after the <hi>Long Vacation:</hi> Our Quarters was at the <hi>King of Beaſts,</hi> and after we had Saluted our Ladies, and bid them Welcome to <hi>Newbury,</hi> we View'd our Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, gave Order for our Supper, and Refreſh'd our ſelves with a Glaſs of good <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy;</hi> and having ſome ſpare time, our Merchant went to Viſit a Friend in Town, and I gave the Ladies an Invitation to take a Walk, which my Miſtreſs was will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to, but her Siſter, being ſomething indiſpoſed after her Journey, deſir'd to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd; and as Good-Luck would have it, the Maid was oblig'd to ſtay with her: So my Charming Widow, after ſhe had diſmantled herſelf of her Riding A couter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and I Augmented the weight of my Buſh, by almoſt half a Pound of P wder, was ready to March; our Landlord underſtanding we were diſpos'd for a Walk, Convey'd us out at his Back-gate, where we found a moſt delicate <hi>Grotte</hi> of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture's not Art's Compoſing, half inviron'd with a Murm'ring Brook whoſe pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſtreams Created a moſt Melodious Harmony, and the whole Compoſure ſeem'd a Second <hi>Paradiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having walk'd a turn or two, I thought it convenient to put my Widow in mind of her Promiſe. Pardon my Preſumption, Madam, ſaid I, in taking the boldneſs, to put you in mind of this Mornings Concluſion, for no fitter opportunity than now can preſent it ſelf; here we are retir'd, and the Place ſeems to be dedicated for the ſame purpoſe. <hi>Sir,</hi> anſwer'd ſhe, <hi>How can I be aſſur'd your Paſſion is Real, ſince your Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quantance is ſo ſlender, in which if I ſhould be deceiv d, how ſhall I be Ridicul d by the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorious World?</hi> I preſume not, Madam, reply'd I, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> lay any Claim of me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing your Eſteem, as to the Quality of my Perſon; nor yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo deſpiſeable in my Deſcent or Fortune, to incur your diſdain. But Love, Almighty Love, who knows no Bounds or Equals, is my Plea; and notwithſtanding my Love is of ſo late a Date, it is as pure as Veſtals Flames, and firm as Fate, and all my Pretenſions Honourable. <hi>If ſo, Sir,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>I do Agnize your Paſſion, and return you mine; for Bluſhing I muſt own it, when firſt I ſaw your Face, an unuſual Flame ſeiz'd my Heart and kindled in my Breaſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nknown Deſires.</hi> At this Confeſſion, I flung my Circling Arms about her Lovely Waſte, and almoſt ſtifled her with Kiſſes. What then remains, cry'd I, my Life, my Soul, but to Quench our Deſires, and delay our Bliſs no longer? At which ſhe ſtarted back, and told me ſhe thought, or ſhe was much miſtaken, before ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd her Paſſion, I declar'd, I deſign'd nothing but what was Honourable; it ſo, what means this unruly Proceeding? Only the extream Ardour of my Flame, my Dear, anſwer'd I; for who can behold the Tempting Tree, and forbear to pluck its Luſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Fruit? <hi>Not till the Prieſt hath made it Lawful, Sir,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>For Fear,—Oh, for Fear.</hi>—By Heaven, and all that's Sacred, Madam, cry'd I, thoſe Fears are Needleſs; for ſooner ſhall the Silver Morn forget to dawn, the Glorious Sun to ſteer its courſe, than I prove falſe to you. What then ſhould hinder us now, from ſatisfying our Craving Appetites, before the Sluggiſh Prieſt hath Crav'd a Bleſſing At which, ſhe ſunk into my Arms, and by her Dying Eyes gave her Conſent; then calling to mind the Alacrity to be us'd in Courting a Widow, and that now might be the Critical Minute, I lad her down on Nature's Carpet and made bold with Mother Earth for a Boulſter; and notwithſtanding all her Faint Reſiſtance, rifled her Joys, Roving through all the hidden Labyrinth of Love, and by our Mutual Embraces Quench'd our ſierce Deſires, then Coo'd and Bill'd like a pair of Amorous Doves, Swearing Eternal Conſtancy afreſh, &amp; to tye the Gordian Knot the firſt opportunity.</p>
            <p>But in our Diſcourſe I took an occaſion to make a ſcrutiny into her Affairs, that I might underſtand what Bargain I was like to have, if I perform'd my Promiſe. She told me ſhe had been a Widow near two years, had no Child, was worth 3000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> and liv'd with her Siſter, who was Married to a Gentleman near <hi>Hackney;</hi> and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo far off, was the reaſon they lay at the Inn laſt Night. This News methought
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:34897:6"/>Augmented her Charms, and having enjoy'd the Shadow, I hop'd in a ſhort time to reap the Golden Subſtance. Having out-ſtaid our time, a Meſſenger came to Deſire us to make haſte, for our Company and Supper waited for us: But when we came, and had given them an Account of our Pleaſant Walk, and Deſcription of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful Grove, (but not a word of the Paradiſe of Love) they ſeem'd to be ſorry they did not go along with us (that neither of us was, I am certain.) Having Supt, they brought us a Bill, which was as reaſonable as a Reckoning at a <hi>Hoſier-Lane</hi> Bawdy-Houſe during <hi>Bartholomow-Fair;</hi> for a Brace of Midling Trouts, they charg'd us but a Leaſh of Crowns, Six Shillings for a Shoulder of <hi>Mutton</hi> and a Plate of <hi>Gerkins,</hi> three and Six-pence for Six <hi>Rowles,</hi> and three Nipperkins of <hi>Belch;</hi> and two Shillings more for <hi>Whip</hi> in Drinking our Healths. Their Wine indeed was good, ſo was their Price; and in a Bill of two Pound four Shillings, they made a Miſtake but of Nine; I ask'd what Countrey-Man my Landlord was? Anſwer was made full <hi>North;</hi> and Faith 'twas very Evident, for he had put the <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> moſt Damnably upon us. But being to riſe very Early, we went to Bed ſoon after we had Supt; and was called by break of Day, my Widow preſented us with a Pot of <hi>Chocolat</hi> of her own Preparing; and filling my Diſhes fuller than ordinary, I Conjectur'd 'twas for my good Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances, daſh'd with a little ſelf-intereſt; after which we recruited our Bottle, and renew'd our Journey; but I marked his Gate with a Croſs as red as the Sign. And before we had Travel'd a Mile, the Ladies laid claim to my promiſe to relate my Story, which I was oblig'd to perform, and was thus.</p>
            <p>There was a very Eminent Shopkeeper in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> had the misfortune to have a very Extravagant Son, who by his Continual Profuſenſs, Conſum'd him a great many Baggs of a certain Commodity much better then <hi>Cherry-Stones;</hi> he was not only very Indulgent to him, but Maintain'd his Family; he being of a Roving Mind, could not Confine himſelf to Buſineſs, but went from his Father and Family, chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his Name, and <hi>Rak'd</hi> about the Town; but by Accident got Acquainted with two Young Women, who kept Shop on the <hi>Royal-Exchange;</hi> the youngeſt of them he Courted for a Wife, and in a ſhort time Married her, made an Extraordinary Figure, and as Mighty Pretences; but he had not Enjoy'd her long before 'twas Diſcover'd, and he Oblig'd to Live with his Firſt, who was no ways deſerving of ſuch an Unkind Action; but rather Worthier of a better Husband; and being ask'd the Reaſon, why he would offer to Commit <hi>Poligamy?</hi> He anſwer'd, <hi>Though Plurality of</hi> Caeſars <hi>was not ſafe for a</hi> State,<hi>Plurality of</hi> Wives <hi>could be no</hi> Crime.</p>
            <p>But the Poor Young Woman was very much Diſappointed; all her hopes Blaſted, and her Promiſing Imaginations prov'd Vain <hi>Chimera's.</hi> For he in a little time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter abandon'd both, and took a Trip to <hi>Jamaica,</hi> where in three Months he Married a Rich Widow, worth at leaſt 7000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr>
               <hi>Sterling,</hi> and before three years was Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated, ſhe made her <hi>Exit;</hi> which he eſteem'd to be the Happyeſt Day in all his Life, the reſult of all his hopes, and the only mark he aim'd at. Now being Maſter of a Plentiful Eſtate, he ſoon Converted it into the Commodity of the Country, and Sail'd for <hi>England,</hi> with a Joyful Heart, and Proſperous Gale; and upon his Arrival at <hi>London,</hi> found himſelf a double Widower, and his <hi>Exchange</hi> Wife Married to a <hi>Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> who was ſo Enamour'd with her Fiz, that notwithſtanding he had heard of her Miſ-fortune, he ty'd the Nooze, and became <hi>One Fleſh,</hi> though of two very different Conſtitutions. She was Young and Airy, and Married him more for the ſake of his Money than Perſon; he Old and Impotent, and as Jealous as a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> by which her Condition was much worſe than before; for on the leaſt Diſtaſte, he would be Reflecting on her former Husband, who had not ſeen her ſince the Diſcovery, nor ſhe him, but heard of his Succeſs, though not by what means he had attain'd it; and was extream Sorry ſhe had Contracted the laſt Marriage; but he having a deſire to ſee her, tho' not to take her again as a Wife, and thinking Time, Abſence, and the Alteration of his Attire, and Hair, (for when he Liv'd with her, he wore his own, but now a Full Wigg) was Diſguiſe ſufficient to Conceal him from her Knowledge; goes to the Shop, and ſhe Congratulated him, with the uſual Complement, of <hi>What do you want Sir?</hi> Two very neceſſary Things, Madam, ſaid he, Clean Gloves and a Pretty Wife; and I Preſume you may ſupply me. <hi>Of the Firſt, Sir,</hi> anſwer'd his Wife,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:34897:6"/>
               <hi>We have Choice; but the laſt is a very ſcarce Commodity, and very difficult to be had.</hi> I was in hopes, Madam, reply'd he, you cou'd have furniſh'd me with both; but more eſpecially the laſt. But ſhe and her Partner both knew him, contrary to his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations: <hi>Sir,</hi> ſaid her Partner, <hi>I am perſwaded you have no occaſion for a</hi> Clogg; <hi>for ſo a Wife is generally Term'd.</hi> But ſuch a Pretty Lady as this is, would be counted rather a Bleſſing. Madam, anſwer'd he. <hi>You wrong your Judgement very much, Sir,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd his Wife, <hi>for Nature hath not been ſo Liberal to me in her Indowments, as you are pleas'd to Flatter me withal. Beſides I am a Wiſe already; and here the dull Animal comes.</hi> As he approach'd the Shop, the other ſpoke to him after this manner: I have been Courting this Lady for a Wife, Sir, but I find you are ſo happy as to be before hand with me. <hi>That's more than be knows, Sir,</hi> ſaid ſhe Smilling. By which he perceiv'd they knew him; but her laſt Husband being Ignorant who he was, took it as a great Affront, and in a mighty Paſſion abus'd her in a very high degree; and Upbraided her with her firſt Husband; which ſo grated his Spirits, that is reviv'd the glowing Embers of his Love, and the conceal'd Sparks broke out into a violent Flame. Thou Mercenary Villain, ſaid he, to Upbraid thy Wife with what her Innocence was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd on; and as I am the Man that was the Agreſſor, I'll do her that Juſtice to make you ask her Pardon, here Publickly on your Knees: Or by <hi>Heaven,</hi> this Moment is your laſt. At which he drew his Sword, and the Glittering Steel ſo ſcar'd poor <hi>Hogan,</hi> that he preſently fell on his Marrowbones, Crav'd her Pardon, and was Glad be came off ſo. Now, Madam, ſaid he, to his Wife, had not you been ſo diſ-ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable to me, on the Diſcovery of my Contract with you, I wou'd have freed you from the Embraces of this Inſipid Coxcomb; but ſince you was ſo Unkind, I can only Condole your ſecond Miſ-fortune, who was ſo Ungrateful to me in your firſt; then departed, and left poor <hi>Butter-Box,</hi> to be ridicul'd by the whole Society of <hi>Thimber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins.</hi> A Friend of mine was an Eye Witneſs of this, and knew both the Husband and Wife. <hi>Without doubt,</hi> ſaid the Gentleman, <hi>This Spark was one of</hi> Solomons <hi>Race, and</hi> Londons <hi>Maſter-Piece.</hi> Oh. Sir, 'tis Reported he is very much Reform'd to what he was; and Lives very Sober and Sedate. <hi>Then it ought to be Chronicl'd for a Miracle,</hi> ſaid he.</p>
            <p>But being come to the rocky Deſcent into <hi>Marlborough,</hi> we were ſo Damnably jolt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that our Merchants Pocket Comfort Vaniſh'd and the Brittle Metal was ſhatter'd into a thouſand pieces; for the Loſs of which, I intail'd ſuch a Hearty Curſe on the Place, that never ſince hath a Coach paſt, but it Over-turn'd, a Waggon or Cart, but it breaks either Wheel or Axeltree, a Horſe, but he Stumbles; and all the Beaſts that Graze near it, Die of the <hi>Murraine:</hi> At laſt with the help of a couple of Gigan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Loobies, to ſupport our Tottering Caravan, we got into the Town, and tipt them a <hi>Hogg</hi> for our ſafe Conduct.</p>
            <p>Being come to <hi>Marlborough,</hi> we broke our faſt at the <hi>Royal-Diadem,</hi> and had Mr. <hi>Mayor</hi> for our Landlord, a good jolly <hi>Bachanalian,</hi> who hath beſtow'd more in adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Fiz, than the Market-houſe coſt Building; &amp; being a Magiſtrate, I made a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Complaint againſt that Curſed Hill, demanded ſatisfaction for the dammage we had ſuſtain'd, in breaking our Brandy Bottle, and told him, unleſs they took ſpeedy Care to have it mended, I would Indite the whole Corporation. <hi>That we cannot do by no means, Sir,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>For in ſo doing we ſhould Ruine half the Town; for the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage that Hill occaſions, brings a Conſiderable Trade to our</hi> Wheel-wrights, Farriers, <hi>and</hi> Chyrurgions; <hi>alſo Creates no ſmall Buſineſs to thoſe of my own Function, and Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains three or four Families to ſupport the Coaches, and aſſiſting at other Accidents: But however, I'll preſent you with a freſh Cargo, and Adviſe you to take more Care for the future:</hi> Before we had Breakfaſted, he was as good as his Word; but to retalliate his Kindneſs, we call'd for two or three Flasks Extraordinary.</p>
            <p>Having lay'd a good Foundation to Travel on, we quitted <hi>Marlborough,</hi> and ſoon came on a curious Down, much Noted for its Flocks of <hi>Grey Weathers,</hi> which often gave us Confounded Jolts, and put us in Mind of our Landlords Caution, concerning our Bottle. But before we had Rod five Mile, we receiv'd Information of a Party of <hi>Light-Horſe</hi> that lay Perdue to Eaſe us of our <hi>Rino.</hi> This News made us look very queer, and my Company to ſink the <hi>Cole</hi> with abundance of Agility. My Miſtreſs was in a Peck of Troubles, for the ſecurity of her Ponderous Purſe; and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:34897:7"/>I thought by the Motion of her Pettycoats, ſhe was a going to put it where my Lady — did her Watch: Our Merchant ſhuffled Looſe <hi>Yellow-Boys</hi> by dozens into the Lining of his Coat, and I Truſted to Providence: But at laſt, to our great Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, it prov'd to be a falſe Alarm, and by the help of our <hi>Nanterian</hi> Cordial, we Recover'd our ſtragling Senſes: The Diſcourſe of which laſted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> till we got to <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy-Lane,</hi> where the Road was ſo Damnable heavy, that two Mile in three hours was an Extraordinary Journey, and the Corporation-Trot to St. <hi>Pauls</hi> on <hi>Sunday,</hi> was a Fool to it: But at Jaſt we Arriv'd at the Sign of <hi>Chevalier Bruint,</hi> where we was to Dine.</p>
            <p>Here we had ſuch an <hi>Amſterdam</hi> W— for our Landlady, that the like was never heard of. She hath Buried five Husbands, never had but one Son, and he was Hang'd; thirteen Daughters, and a Dozen of them was of their Mothers Stamp, and the other Dy'd an Infant; the Old one was a Widow, her Daughters Maids, yet between them had more Children, then <hi>Roſemary-Lane</hi> aſſords on a <hi>Sunday;</hi> and moſt of their <hi>Sires</hi> was <hi>Souldiers</hi> or <hi>Cattle-Firkers.</hi> There was more Coaches and Waggons, drawn up before her Gate, then Hacks in <hi>Palace-Yard,</hi> during the <hi>Seſſions of Parliament,</hi> or <hi>Term-Time.</hi> All her Entertainment is Loins of <hi>Mutton,</hi> or <hi>Rabbets;</hi> and ſhe makes more Broth in a Day, then all the <hi>Chop-Houſes</hi> in <hi>Caſtle-Alley</hi> in a Week. At laſt, with much ado, we got two of the aforeſaid Diſhes for Dinner, and a Naſty Jade to Attend us; who, as we underſtood afterwards, was one of her Daughters; but by her Looks, one would Conjecture the Devil was her Father; yet ſhe was Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to us, for the Flower of them all: But in my Judgment the Old one is more inviting than any of her Off-Spring. The beſt Accommodation we had there, was the Juice of Pippins, which we Drank very Plentifully, but by it's Urinical motion, hindred <hi>Whip</hi> one Mile in four; and the Ladies Emiſſary, Miſtreſs <hi>Pert,</hi> once was ſo hard put to it, that we thought by her Soure Looks, and the wringing of her Knees, ſhe had the <hi>Dry-Gripes;</hi> but at laſt a Natural Evacuation gave her Eaſe, and Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> great deal of Laughter. Our Bill was compos'd in a few Words; and was very Moderate, conſidering what Extravagant Prices, we often give for <hi>Mutton</hi> and <hi>Conny</hi> in ſome Places.</p>
            <p>Having Din'd, we proceeded on our Journey, but with a great of diſſiculty; for the Road was ſo Rocky, Unlevel, and Narrow in ſome Places, that! am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the <hi>Alps</hi> are to be paſſed with leſs danger, in the Performance of which, our firking <hi>Eſſedarian</hi> was oblig'd to uſe abundance of Horſe-Courting-Rhetorick to his Tired <hi>Ambulators;</hi> and when that prevail'd not, to Exerciſe his Tickler; but we were jolted ſo Curſedly, that I thought it would have made a diſlocation of my Bones; we all complain'd, but could find no Remedy; nor would I Adviſe any who have been Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferers in <hi>Venus</hi> ſports, to Adventure the Fatigue of a Coach to the <hi>Bath,</hi> leaſt it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynt a Member or two. At laſt when our Patience was almoſt worn out, we agreed to light rather than endure it any longer; but out Chariotier inform'd us, we were almoſt at our Journeys-end, which we preſently found to be true, and <hi>Bath</hi> was as Welcome to us, as a good Dinner to a <hi>Covent-Garden</hi> Tooth-Picker.</p>
            <p>Being come to the <hi>White-Hart,</hi> our long wiſh'd-for Port, we refreſhed our ſelves with much Joy, after our tedious Mortifying-Journey: And there our Merchant took his Leave of us, in a freſh Coach for <hi>Briſhtol:</hi> Then Enquiring for a Lodging, we were recommended to a <hi>Tonſors,</hi> whoſe Wife kept a <hi>Milliners-Shop</hi> in the ſame Houſe, where was Accommodation for us all, tho' he had ſeveral other Lodgers in the Houſe, of good Quality. That Night my Widow and I had an opportunity to enjoy our ſelves to our Mutual Satisfaction, without any ſuſpicion, and agreed to be made one Fleſh, the firſt opportunity that offer'd. In the Morning we were ſaluted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by the whole Fraternity of <hi>Cat-Gut-Scrapers,</hi> and cou'd not get rid of them without the Aſſiſtance of an Angel. My Miſtreſs and her Siſter would not appear Publick, till their Baggage Arriv'd from <hi>London,</hi> which they did not expect in three or four days, ſo I had the Liberty ſtroul alone.</p>
            <p>After I had Accouter'd my ſelf to the beſt Advantage, (in which I made no ſmall Figure) I went to the Coffee-Houſe, where I found ſeveral of my Acquaintance, who ſeem'd to be Over-joy'd at my Appearance, Imbrac'd and Slabber'd me, as an Old Woman does her Grand Child; asking a thouſand Impertinent Queſtions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>London,</hi> and what Company came with me? If Ladies, or Gentlement? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:34897:7"/>my Quality was on the Road bound for the <hi>Bath?</hi> In which I ſatisfied them to the beſt of my knowledge; but after we had taken a diſh or two, of that inſipid Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, we Adjourn'd to Honeſt <hi>C</hi>— at the <hi>Three T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> where we Enliven'd our Souls with a Glaſs of good <hi>Burdeaux,</hi> and ſparkling <hi>Sherry;</hi> and from thence we went to ſee the Diverſion of the <hi>Baths.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of which, 'tis not my Deſign to give you an Account of their <hi>Original,</hi> and Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent <hi>Cures;</hi> or a Deſcription of their <hi>Structure,</hi> and Noble <hi>Founders;</hi> for that's al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready perform'd, in moſt of our Chronicles; but ſhall only hint on the <hi>Ways</hi> and <hi>Intrigues</hi> that are manag'd there during the Seaſon.</p>
            <p>The firſt we went to, is call'd the <hi>Kings;</hi> and to it joyns the <hi>Queen's,</hi> both run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in one; and the moſt famous for Cures. In this <hi>Bath</hi> wee at leaſt Fifty of both Sexes, with a Score or two of Guides, who by their Scorbutick Carcaſſes, and Lacker'd Hides, you would think they had lain Pickling a Century of Years in the <hi>Stygian Lake:</hi> Some had thoſe Infernal Emiſſaries to ſupport their Impotent Limbs: Others to ſcrub their Putrify'd Carcaſſes, like a Race-Florſe. In one Corner was an Old Fornicator hanging by the Rings, Loaded with a Rotten Humidity: Hard by him was a Boxom Dame, Cleanſing her <hi>Nunquam Satis</hi> from <hi>Mercurial</hi> Dregs and the remains of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Vitriol.</hi> Another, half cover'd with Sear-Cloth, had more Sores than <hi>Lazarus,</hi> doing Pennance for the Sins of her Youth; At her Elbow was a Young Hero, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by a couple of Guides, rack'd with Aches and Intolerable Pains, Curſing of <hi>Middleſex</hi> Court, and <hi>Beveridges</hi> Dancing-School, as Heartily as <hi>Job</hi> the Day of his Birth. At the Pump was ſeveral a Drenching their Gullets, and Gormandizing the Reaking Liquor by Wholeſale.</p>
            <p>From thence we went to the <hi>Croſs-Bath,</hi> where moſt of the Quality reſorts, more Fam'd for Pleaſure then Cures, tho' they pretend it hath wrought Miracles on Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren-Soil, and wonderfully helps Conception. Not long ſince, a Gentleman of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity was beholden to it for an Heir, as he reported; but his Lady is of a contrary Opinion; yet I know not what Operation ſuch Tempting Objects may have by cauſing Titilation, and heighten Imagination, to procure an immediate Conjunction. Here is perform'd all the Wanton Dalliancies imaginable; Celebrated Beauties, Panting Breaſts, and Curious Shapes, almoſt Expos'd to Publick View; Languiſhing Eyes, Darting Killing Glances, Tempting Amorous Poſtures, attended by ſoft Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, enough to provoke a <hi>Veſtal</hi> to forbidden Pleaſure, Captivate a <hi>Saint,</hi> and Charm a <hi>Jove:</hi> Here was alſo different Sexes, from Quality to the Honourable <hi>Knights,</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try <hi>Put,</hi> and City <hi>Madam</hi>'s: Nay, the Circumciz'd <hi>Jew,</hi> could <hi>Bathe</hi> in Delight, <hi>Swim</hi> in Pleaſure with the <hi>Gentile,</hi> &amp; out-vie a Courtier in Splendor, tho' they Crucifi'd his God; and Diſpence with <hi>Chriſtians-Flaſh,</hi> tho' not with <hi>Swines.</hi> The Ladies with their floating <hi>Jappan</hi>-Bowles, freighted with Confectionary Knick-Knacks, Eſlences, &amp; Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes, Wade about, like <hi>Neptune</hi>'s Courtiers, ſuppling their Induſtrious Joynts. The Vigorous Sperks, preſenting them with ſeveral Antick Poſtures, as Sailing on their Backs, then Embracing the Element, ſink in a Rapture, and by Accidental Deſign, thruſt a ſtretch'd Arm; but where the Water conceal'd, ſo ought my Pen.</p>
            <p>The Spectators in the Galleries, pleaſing their Roving Fancies with this Ladies Face, anothers Eyes, a thirds heaving Breaſts, and Profound Air. In one Corner ſtood an Old Letcher, whoſe years ſpoke him no leſs then threeſcore and ten, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Love to a Young Lady, not exceeding fourteen. The uſual time being come to forſake that ſickle Element, <hi>Half-Tub Chairs,</hi> Lin'd with Blankets, Ply'd as thick, as <hi>Coaches</hi> at the <hi>Play-Houſe,</hi> or <hi>Carts</hi> at the <hi>Cuſtom-Houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bathing being over for that Day, we went to walk in the Grove, a very pleaſant Place for Diverſion; there is the <hi>Royal-Oak</hi> and ſeveral Raffling Shops: In one of the Walks, is ſeveral Sets of Nine-Pins, and Attendance to wait on you: Tipping all Nine for a Guinea, is as common there, as two Farthings for a <hi>Porringer</hi> of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley-Broth,</hi> at the <hi>Hoſpital-Gate</hi> in <hi>Smithfield.</hi> On ſeveral of the Trees was hung a Lampoon on the Marriage of one Mr. <hi>S</hi>— a Drugmonger, and the famous Madam <hi>S</hi>— an old <hi>B</hi>— of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having almoſt tir'd our ſelves with walking, we took to a Bench to eaſe our wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Pedeſtals. Now, ſaid my Friend, I'll give you an impartial Account of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, Qualities and Functions, of a few particular Perſons that are among
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:34897:8"/>this Amphibious Crowd. For notwithſtanding I have been here not above a Fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, I am as well acquainted with the Town and its Intrigues, as old Juſtice <hi>P</hi>— with <hi>More-fields</hi> and <hi>Drury-Lane</hi> Bawdy-Houſes.</p>
            <p>Thoſe two Ladies with the Gentleman in Blew, are Siſters, live near the Church that is Dedicated to a Saint who expir'd on a Gridiron, they are Amorous Dames; the Gentleman is a Broken Officer, and lives better on their Allowances, than he could on his Pay. This gentlewoman in the White-Damesk Cown, is a Sea-Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains Lady; who, while her Corniferous Mate is Plowing the Ocean, takes Care to Manure his <hi>Paſture,</hi> that he may have a Fruitful Crop this Harveſt. That Foppiſh <hi>Beau</hi> in Scarlet Stockings, whoſe Hilt of his Sword bears a bob with his Calves, and his Jubilee Hatband lies ſtitch'd croſs the Crown, was a Pettycoat-Penſioner to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>C</hi>—near <hi>Bucklersbury;</hi> but being lately Diſcarded, is come down here for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion. That young Lady with the Gold Orice Pettycoat, was a great Fortune, and not long ſince was Married to a Flannel Waſtecoat, and a double Night-Cap of the ſame Stuff; but now by reaſon of her Husbands Imbecility, is forc'd to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the <hi>Bath.</hi> That Tall Gentleman attended by three Liveries, is ſomething of Quality, a right Courtier, for he abhors the Cirizens Wives as much as the Sword-Bearer does <hi>Cuſtard.</hi> That <hi>Broad-price</hi> Doctor, in the Diminutive Band, makes a Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe every year by the Wickedneſs of the Age; and Vindicates <hi>W</hi>—<hi>ing</hi> more than ever <hi>G.K</hi>—Writ againſt the Quakers. That Pert young Gentlewoman with the two Silver Fringes, was compell'd by her Friends to Marry a Slovenly <hi>Stechjobber,</hi> and now is ſurfeited with his Embraces; and came to the <hi>Bath</hi> to mend his Breed. That Crafty Prieſt, that Son of <hi>Levi,</hi> is as fickle as a Weather-Cock, and would ſooner diſcard a good Conſcience, then a fat Benefice. This Tun of Iniquity, in the Crim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Gown, with <hi>Monſicur</hi> at her Elbow, two <hi>Dewils</hi> behind her, and <hi>Aetna</hi> in her Face, all the Water in the <hi>Severn</hi> is not able to Quench her deſires; ſhe is a ſecond <hi>Maſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lina,</hi> will tire, but ne'er be ſatisfi'd; ſhe hath already quarter'd a Troop of <hi>French</hi> Dragoons, a Regiment of <hi>Dutchmen,</hi> and now is come to Exerciſe a Battalion of <hi>Brittains.</hi> That Powder'd <hi>Labſter</hi> in the Edg'd Hat, is the Spawn of a <hi>Broker;</hi> from thence Evapulated to a <hi>Bully,</hi> now ſhams an <hi>Officer,</hi> ſets up for a <hi>Stallion</hi> of the firſt Rank, and pretends he receives ſeveral Favours from a Qualitificated Lady. That Spark with his Hat under his Arm, is a Limb of the Law, but hath Studied <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlins</hi> Midwifry, more than <hi>Cook</hi>'s Reports. That <hi>Dowdy Minx</hi> in the Scarlet Top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and Pink'd Scarff, is the Relick of a broken <hi>Grocer;</hi> an Induſtrious Woman, for her Head's no ſooner lay'd, but her Breech is at Work. In ſhort, for <hi>Fops, Beaus,</hi> and <hi>Bellfa's,</hi> this Place exceeds <hi>Greys-Inn-Walks</hi> on <hi>Sunday</hi> Evening; and conſiſts of greater variety of Perſons, Remarkable for ſome Vice or Folly, than there are Ingredients in a Lombard-Pye for a City Feaſt; to give you a particular Deſcription of each of 'em, will require a Weeks time at leaſt. Come therefore, let's go to ſome Tipling Manſion, and Carouſe, till we have Exbilerated our Drowthy Souls: To which I readily agreed. About five in the Evening, we went to a ſee a great <hi>Match</hi> at Bowling; there was <hi>Quality,</hi> and Reverend <hi>Doctors</hi> of both Profeſſions, Topping <hi>Merchants,</hi> Broken <hi>Bankers,</hi> Noted <hi>Mercers,</hi> Inns-of Court <hi>Rales,</hi> City <hi>Beaus,</hi> Stray'd <hi>Prentices,</hi> and <hi>Dancing-Maſters</hi> in abundance. <hi>Fly, fly, fly, fly;</hi> ſaid one: <hi>Rub, rub, rub, rub,</hi> cry'd another. <hi>Ten Guinies to five, I <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncover the</hi> Jack, ſays a third, <hi>Danon theſe Nice Fingers of mine,</hi> cry'd my Lord, <hi>I Slipt my Bowl, and miſtook the Bias.</hi> Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Swearing he knew the Ground to an Inch, and would hold five Pound his Bowl came in. But in ſhort, the Citizens won the Courtiers Money, and the Courtiers Swore to be Reveng'd on their Wives, and Daughters.</p>
            <p>From hence we went to the <hi>Groom-Porters,</hi> where they were a Labouring like ſo many <hi>Ancher-Smiths,</hi> at the <hi>Oake, Bach Gammon, Tick-Tack, Iriſh, Baſſet,</hi> and throwing of <hi>Mains.</hi> There was Palming, Lodging, Loaded Dice, Levant, and Gammoning, with all the Speed imaginable; but the <hi>Corniſh</hi> Rook was too hard for them all. The <hi>Briſtol Fair</hi> Sparks had but a very had Bargain of it; and little occaſion for Returns. <hi>Bank-Bills,</hi> and <hi>Exchequer-Notes,</hi> were as Plenty, as <hi>Fops</hi> at the <hi>Chocolat-Houſes,</hi> or <hi>Pater-noſter-Row.</hi> Having ſatisfied our Curioſity here; we leſt them as buſie a ſhaking their Elbows, as the <hi>Apple-woman</hi> in <hi>Stocks-Market,</hi> Wallnuts in <hi>October.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And meeting with three or four more Acquaintance, we Stroul'd to a <hi>Briſtol-Milk
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:34897:8"/>Dary-Houſe,</hi> and Enjoy'd ourſelves like brave <hi>Bacchanalians.</hi> At Night I ſtole into my Miſtreſſes Arms, as Vigorous, as Youth, Beauty, Wine and Love, could inſpire me; but ſhe urging mightily for a ſpeedy Marriage, which I was not very back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to, we agreed to be Riveted the next Morning; ſhe undertaking to ingage the Maid to Aſſiſt her, and I, our Landlord, to procure a Miniſter; which accordingly was perform'd the next day, with a great deal of Secreſie, at the Expence of half a ſcore Guineas; and Spouſe deſir'd it might not be known while we continu'd in the Country, for ſome particular Reaſons. Now being joyn'd by the Prieſt, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>Bride,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Pert,</hi> managed it ſo, that we lay together without any Miſtruſt. <hi>Let a Woman alone for a Contrivance, to obtain her Deſires.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About Ten in the Morning, I was ſent for by ſome Acquaintance, to the general Rendezvouz—<hi>Coffee-Houſe,</hi> where Fools, Cullies, Squires, Beaus, &amp; Criticks, reſort as thick, as <hi>Stock-Jobbers</hi> about the Effigies on the <hi>Royal-Exchange;</hi> here Witiciſm was Abdicated, and Nonſence banded to and fro, like a Shuttle-Cock. The laſt Nights Intrigue Whiſper'd with abundance of Caution, and that Nights Ball was Prognoſticated would be very Noble, for 'twas given by a Lady of Quality, and after an hour or two of their inſipid Fuſtian and Block-headly Combate, we went to Raffle for a Preſent for our Miſtreſſes; and with the loſs of a Guinea, I brought off a curious Snuſh-Box, worth four: But tho' I was Fortunes Favorite, ſhe Bilk'd a young Mercer of twenty <hi>Jacobuſſes,</hi> and at the <hi>Oake</hi> the ſame Night double the Number, and a Bay Gelding.</p>
            <p>From thence we went to the <hi>Hot-Bath,</hi> and <hi>Leapers-Bath,</hi> but there was nothing worth our Obſervation, but a parcel of old Crutches, hung up in Memory of the Perſons that receiv'd thoſe Miraculous Cures. The next place we adjourn'd to, was to <hi>Herrid Tones;</hi> where we had good Wine, and better Company; and being my Wedding-Day, I went home to Dine with my Bride, and in the Evening pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd with her to go to the Ball.</p>
            <p>Which is always kept at the Town-Hall, a very ſpacious Room, and fitted up for that Purpoſe. During which, the Door is kept by a couple of Brawny Beadles, to keep out the Mobility, looking as fierce as the Uncouth Figures at <hi>Guild-Hall;</hi> there was Extraordinary Fine Dancing, (and how cou'd it otherwiſe chuſe?) for Spouſe and I had a Hand in it. A Conſort of Delicate Muſick, Vocal and Inſtrumental, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd by good Maſters: A Noble Collation of dry Sweet-Meats, Rich Wine, and Large Attendance. The Lady who was the <hi>Doner,</hi> wore an Extraordinary Rich Favour, to diſtinguiſh her from the reſt, which is always the Cuſtome; and before they break up, to chuſe another for the next Day, which fell upon a Shentleman of <hi>Wales;</hi> but nor no ways Derogated from her Honour, or Diſperag'd her Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey in the leaſt, but hur was as Noble, and as Generous, as e'er an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Shentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of them all: To hur Honour be it Spoke.</p>
            <p>The next Day the Ladies Baggage Arriv'd from <hi>London;</hi> then they made as top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping a Figure as any of them are, and the firſt Night after their Publick Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, we were ſo troubl'd with ſome Serenading Coxcombs, that the whole Family got up, and had not Mrs. <hi>Betty,</hi> been vigilant, my new Adopted Fleſh and I, had been catch'd abed together; for which good Service, I rewarded her with a broad piece of her own Name. A <hi>Sunday</hi> we went to Church to the Abby, a very Ancient Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral piece of Antiquity, and kept as badly in repair; 'tis Crowded during Divine Service, as much as St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> in which time there is more Billet Deaux convey'd to the Ladies, than Notes to deſire the Prayers of the Congregation at <hi>B</hi>'s—Meeting-Houſe: And as the Ingenious Doctor in his Diſcourſe, told the Audience, <hi>He was afraid moſt of them came more out of Cuſtome and Formality, than in Devotion to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Deity, or a ſuitable Reverence to the Place of Worſhip.</hi> Which was very True, I am Confident, and the Ladies were the only Saints ſeveral came there to Adore; as this Billet Deaux will confirm; it was convey'd in a Candid Orange to a Lady in one of the Galleries, which ſhe by Accident dropt, and I had the Fortune to find.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Had Fortune that Fickle Goddeſs, but Honour'd me with your Acquaintance, as ſhe has by ſeeing of your Perſon, I ſhould not have been ſo Preſumptuous, as to have offer'd theſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:34897:9"/>imperfect Lines to your fair Hands; but ſince my Cruel Stars ordain'd me no ſuch happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, I was forc'd to make my Pen become my Orator, and Commit that to Writing which ought rather to have been Pay'd by Adoration. At ſix this Evening I ſhall be in the Meadows; Pity your Slave, and Grant me ſome Relief.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>R.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>In the Evening we took a Walk into the Meadows, much reſorted to for plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Rivers, and delicate Walks; 'tis a ſecond <hi>Hide-Park</hi> for Coaches, and a St. <hi>James</hi>'s for <hi>Beau</hi>'s and <hi>Belfa</hi>'s of all ſorts; there was <hi>Chaucer</hi>'s Sempſtreſs, my Lord <hi>R</hi>— Mantua-Makers dandled by Cringing Fops, Antick Beaus, and Bluſtering Bullies Innumerable, <hi>London-Jilts</hi> with Tails like Counteſſes, and caſe-harden'd Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence; bantering Young Squires, and Shopkeepers Prentices: Nay my Millenian Landlady, and her Siſter, was there Intriguing, and as well match'd as a pair of Nice Coach-Horſes; much Admired, the one for an obliging Temper, the other for a Beauty; but ask honeſt <hi>Punch</hi> the <hi>Paſtry-Cook,</hi> he'll tell you they Rival each other in their own proper Qalifications.</p>
            <p>After an Hour or two's Walking, I Treated my Ladies with the beſt the Place afforded, and then returned Home: But the next Morning I receiv'd a Letter of Advice from <hi>London,</hi> of the Death of an Aunt, who had made me her Heir; which put me in mind of the Old Proverb, <hi>It never Rains, but muſt Pour.</hi> However this was no ill News to my Bride, nor me neither; only requiring my ſpeedy appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance at <hi>London;</hi> but I promiſed Spouſe, and the reſt of my Acquaintance, to be with them again in a Fortnights time, and tho' an Heir, took Leave of them with as much Regret, as the <hi>Dutch-Guards</hi> of <hi>Kenſington;</hi> and the next Morning took Poſt for <hi>London.</hi> Having now given you an Account of my ſucceſsful Step, I'll make bold, and give you my Sentiments of the <hi>BATH.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="description">
               <head>A Character of the <hi>BATH.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>'TIS neither Town nor City, yet goes by the Name of both; five Months in the Year 'tis as Populous as <hi>London,</hi> the other ſeven as deſolate as a Wilderneſs. It's chiefeſt Inhabitants are Turn-ſpit-Dogs; and it looks like <hi>Lombard-Street</hi> on a Saints-day. During the Seaſon, it hath as many Families in a Houſe as <hi>Edenborough;</hi> and Bills are as thick for Lodgings to be Let, as there was for Houſes in the <hi>Pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars</hi> on the Late Act of Parliament for the Diſſolution of Priviledges; but when the <hi>Baths</hi> are uſeleſs, ſo are their Houſes, and as empty as the new Buildings by St. <hi>Giles</hi> in the Fields: The <hi>Baths</hi> I can compare to nothing but the <hi>Boylers</hi> in <hi>Fleet-lane</hi> or <hi>Old-Bedlam,</hi> for they have a reaking ſteem all the year. In a word, 'tis a Valley of Pleaſure, yet a ſink of Iniquity; nor is there any Intrigues or Debauch Acted at <hi>London,</hi> but is Mimick'd there.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:34897:9"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
